<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC3493 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3493.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC4861 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC4862 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC3484 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3484.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC5014 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5014.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC6059 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6059.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC6275 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6275.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC3971 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3971.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC4191 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4191.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC3549 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3549.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC5213 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC5226 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC6724 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6724.xml'>

    <!ENTITY API PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.liu-dmm-mobility-api.xml'>
    <!ENTITY CLASS PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.bhandari-dhc-class-based-prefix.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>


<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc autobreaks="yes" ?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" 
updates="4861, 4862"
docName="draft-korhonen-6man-prefix-properties-02.txt">
 <front>
  <title abbrev="IPv6 Prefix Properties">IPv6 Prefix Properties</title>
  <author initials='J.' surname="Korhonen" fullname='Jouni Korhonen'>
   <organization abbrev="Renesas Mobile">Renesas Mobile</organization>
   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>Porkkalankatu 24</street>
     <code>FIN-00180 Helsinki</code>
     <country>Finland</country>
    </postal>
    <email>jouni.nospam@gmail.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>

  <author initials="B" surname="Patil" fullname="Basavaraj Patil">
   <organization>Cisco</organization>
   <address>
    <email>bpatil1@gmail.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="Sri Gundavelli" initials="S" surname="Gundavelli">
   <organization abbrev="">Cisco</organization>
   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
     <city>San Jose</city>
     <region>CA</region>
     <code>95134</code>
     <country>USA</country>
    </postal>
    <email>sgundave@cisco.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>

  <author fullname="Pierrick Seite" initials="P." surname="Seite">
   <organization>France Telecom - Orange</organization>
   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>4, rue du Clos Courtel, BP 91226</street>
     <city>Cesson-Sevigne</city>
     <code>35512</code>
     <country>France</country>
    </postal>
    <email>pierrick.seite@orange.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>

  <author fullname="Dapeng Liu" initials="D." surname="Liu">
   <organization>China Mobile</organization>
   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>32 Xuanwumen West Street</street>
     <city>Beijng, Xicheng District</city>
     <code>100053</code>
     <country>China</country>
    </postal>
    <email>liudapeng@chinamobile.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>

  <date year="2013"/>
  <area>Internet</area>
  <workgroup>Distributed Mobility Management (DMM)</workgroup>
  
  <abstract>
   <t>This specification defines an extension to the IPv6 Neighbor
    Discovery protocol and the stateless address autoconfiguration procedure.
    A new Prefix Information Option with meta data is defined that describe the
    properties and other prefix class meta data associated with the prefix. The 
    stateless address autoconfiguration procedure and end hosts can
    make use of the additional properties and class information when selecting
    prefixes for a particular uses and use cases. This specification updates 
    RFC4861 and RFC4862.
   </t>
  </abstract>

  <note title="Requirements Language">
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
   document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
   target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
  </note>
 </front>

 <middle>
  <section title="Introduction">
   <t>This specification defines an extension to the IPv6 Neighbor
   Discovery protocol and its Prefix Information Option (PIO) <xref     
   target="RFC4861"/>. The Prefix Information Option is extended with flag bits
   that
   describe, for example, the mobility management properties associated
   to the prefix, and a class value that conveys metadata associated to
   the prefix with local administrative domain wide importance.
   Furthermore, the specification discusses corresponding source address
   selection hint flags to the IPv6 Socket API for Source Address
   Selection <xref target="RFC5014"/>.
   </t>
   <t>For example, the IPv6 Socket API for Source Address Selection <xref target="RFC5014"/>
   already covers Mobile IPv6 <xref target="RFC6275"/> and allows selecting between a
   home address (HoA) and a care-of address (CoA).  A mobile node (MN)
   with a client based mobility IP stack is supposed to know which
   prefixes are CoA(s) and/or HoA(s).  However, this is not the case with
   network based mobility management where the MN is expected to be
   agnostic of the mobility support. There has been attemps in past to define similar
   functionality for the mobility protocols purposes <xref target="I-D.damic-6man-pmip6-ind"/>.
    Outside the mobility protocols,
   there are other potential use cases where associating properties to
   the advertised prefixes could be useful as discussed in 
   <xref target="I-D.bhandari-dhc-class-based-prefix"/>.
   </t>
   <t>The extensions to  <xref target="RFC4861"/> are minimal in a sense that
    they do not define new functionality to, for example, any existing mobility
    protocol but
    instead add an explicit indication of network based mobility knowledge into
    the IPv6 stateless address autoconfiguration (SLAAC). 
   </t>
   <t>This  would allow for network based mobility solutions, such as Proxy 
    Mobile IPv6 <xref target="RFC5213"/> or GTP <xref target="TS.29274"/> to 
    explicitly indicate that their prefixes have mobility, and therefore, the MN 
    IP stack can make an educated selection between prefixes that have mobility 
    and those that do not. There is also a potential need to extend both <xref 
    target="RFC3493"/> and <xref target="RFC5014"/> in order to provide required 
    hooks into socket APIs. 
   </t>
   <t>The underlying assumption is that a MN has multiple prefixes to
   choose from.  Typically this means either the MN has multiple
   interfaces or an interface has been configured with multiple
   prefixes.  This specification does not make a distinction between
   these alternatives and does not either make any assumptions how the
   possible transfer of a prefix is done between interfaces in the case
   a network based mobility solution is used.
   </t>
  </section>
  
  <section title="Background and Motivation">
  <t> This section discusses the motivations behind adding metadata and
  other address selection decision making affecting information into
  IPv6 prefixes. The additional information is convey from the network
  to a end host during the IPv6 address configuration phase. The motivation
  example taken from and discussed below is from the mobile networks.
  </t>
   <t>IP mobility and its centralized topological anchoring of IP addresses
    has known issues. For instance, non-optimal routing is a classical example.
    Another concerns include excessive tunneling, increased signaling due the
    maintenance of mobility related bindings, aggregation of traffic to centralized
    mobility anchor gateways and unnecessary IP mobility related state management
    for IP traffic that does not as such benefit from mobility. In general, it is
    observed that most applications do not need IP level mobility, and work just
    fine with "temporary" IP addresses that come and go. However, IP mobility still
    has its virtues making the applications unaware of mobility, and certain wireless
    mobile networking architecture make extensive use of network based IP mobility.
   </t>
   <t>In order to overcome some of the above issues, use of local resources and
    topologically local addressing could be enhanced. In many cases this would
    lead to use of multiple addresses of which some provide mobility and some do
    not. However, an end host has to have means to distinguish between addresses
    that provide mobility, and those that are short lived and usable only within
    a limited topological area. This specification provides extensions to IPv6
    address management and source address selection so that end hosts (and their
    applications) can select a proper address for their needs.
   </t>
   <t>This specification also shares similar motivations for classifying the 
    prefix properties as described in <xref target="I-D.bhandari-dhc-class-based-prefix"/>.
    This specification complements
    <xref target="I-D.bhandari-dhc-class-based-prefix"/> by providing the
    SLAAC version of the additional prefix related information delivery 
    compared to the DHCPv6 stateful approach.
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Option Formats" anchor="options">
   <section title="Prefix Information Option with Meta Data" anchor="piomt">
  
   <t>This specification defines a new neighbor discovery protocol 
    message option, the Prefix Information Option with Meta Data (PIOMT), to be
    used in router advertisement messages. The PIOMT is treated exactly the
    same as RFC4861 <xref target="RFC4861"/> Prefix Information Option (PIO)
    except with an addition of new meta data suboptions.
   </t>
   <t>The PIOMT can coexist with RFC4861 PIO. The prefixes advertised in 
   both PIOMT and PIO can even be the same. It is up to the receiving end
   host to select the appropriate prefix(es) for configuring its IPv6
   addresses. In a case the PIO and the PIOMT share the same prefix, then
   all the other parameter (like flags and lifetimes) MUST be the same.

   <figure title="Prefix Information Option with additional meta data" anchor="fig_piomt">
<artwork><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |      Type     |    Length     | Prefix Length |L|A| Reserved1 |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                         Valid Lifetime                        |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                       Preferred Lifetime                      |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                            Reserved2                          |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                                                               |
    +                                                               +
    |                                                               |
    +                            Prefix                             +
    |                                                               |
    +                                                               +
    |                                                               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    :                          Suboptions                           :
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
   </figure>
   </t>

   <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
    <t hangText="Type"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
     Set to TBD1.
    </t>

    <t hangText="Length"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
     4 if no suboptions are present. Greater than 4 if one or more suboptions
     ar present.
    </t>

    <t hangText="Suboptions"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
     Zero or more suboptions that describe properties and other meta data
     attached to the advertised prefix. See <xref target="suboptions"/> for
     description of the meta data suboption format and suboptions already
     defined in this specification. The existence of suboptions can be 
     determined from the length field. If the length is greater than 4, then
     at least one suboption is present.
    </t>
    </list>
   </t> 
   <t>Rest of the fields are handled exactly as described in Section 4.6.2. of
    RFC4861 <xref target="RFC4861"/>.
   </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Meta Data Suboptions" anchor="suboptions">
   <t>The generic suboption format for the PIO with meta data is shown in
    <xref target="mt_generic"/>.  The suboption follows the alignment and
    length rules familiar from RFC4861 <xref target="RFC4861"/>. On a particular
    note, the flag 'C' describes whether the suboption is mandatory to
    understand by the receiver or not. If 'C' is set to zero (0), the receiver
    can silently discard an unknown suboption and skip to the next suboption. 
    If 'C' is set to one (1), then an unknown suboption causes the receiver to 
    silently discard the entire PIO with meta data and no further suboptions
    need to be parsed.

   <figure title="Generic meta data suboption format" anchor="mt_generic">
<artwork><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |     Type      |    Length     |C|          Reserved           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                              ...                              ~
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
   </figure>
   </t>


   <!-- ============================================= -->
   <t><xref target="mt_properties"/> shows the Prefix Properties suboption.
   The prefix properties values are defined in Section 6.1. of 
   <xref target="I-D.bhandari-dhc-class-based-prefix"/>. When an end host
   receives a router advertisement message with a PIOMT and the prefix 
   properties suboption, it can use the suboption information as an additional
   hint for selecting the prefix for a desired purpose and use case.


   <figure title="Prefix Properties suboption" anchor="mt_properties">
<artwork><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |       0       |        1      |C|         Reserved1           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |        Prefix properties      |           Reserved2           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
   </figure>
   </t>

   <!-- ============================================= -->

   <t><xref target="mt_class"/> shows the Prefix Class suboption.
   The prefix class values and usage follow what has been defined in Section 
   2.3. of <xref target="I-D.bhandari-dhc-class-based-prefix"/>. When an end 
   host receives a router advertisement message with a PIOMT and the prefix 
   class suboption, it can use the suboption information as an additional
   hint for selecting the prefix for a desired purpose and use case.
 
   <figure title="Prefix Class suboption" anchor="mt_class">
<artwork><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |       1       |        1      |C|         Reserved1           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |         Prefix class          |           Reserved2           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
   </figure>
   </t>

   <t>Future specifications MAY define new suboptions. One potential example
   could be a suboption to identify the provisioning domain where the
   configuration information originates.
   </t>
   </section>
  </section>
  
  <section title="Host Considerations">
   <section title="Stateless Address Autoconfiguration Enhancements">
    <t>This specification extends to the RFC4862 <xref target="RFC4862"/>
    Stateless Address Autoconfiguration (SLAAC).
    </t>
   </section>
   <section title="Internal Data Structures">
    <t>The host internal data structures need to be extended with the 'prefix 
     Property' and the 'prefix Class' information associated to the learned
     prefix and configured 
     addresses. How this is accomplished is host implementation specific. It is 
     also a host implementation issue how an application can learn or query
     both Properties or Class of an address or a prefix. One possibility is to 
     provide such information through the socket API extensions (see discussion 
     in <xref target="I-D.liu-dmm-mobility-api"/>). Other possibilities include 
     the use of e.g., ioctl() or NetLink <xref target="RFC3549"/> extensions.
    </t>
    <t><list>
      <t>[Editor's note: The SLAAC procedure using the CPIO and the 'Class'
      meta data to be described in more detail.]</t>
    </list></t>
   </section>

   <section title="Default Address Selection">
    <t>The 'prefix Property' is only used as
    a hint.  They do not affect the existing <xref target="RFC6724"/> 
    automatically. A specific rule
     to host's policy table has to be inserted by 
    an application or some daemon process. Alternatively, an application can 
    express its address mobility property preferences through the socket API 
    extensions (see discussion in <xref target="I-D.liu-dmm-mobility-api"/>), 
    which means the socket library or middleware has to modify <xref 
    target="RFC6724"/> policy table or algorithm.
    </t>
   <t>The 'prefix Properties' flags MAY define the prefix preference for an IP
    stack that  understands the extensions defined in this specification. The IP
    stack  SHOULD use the Properties preferences to supersede <xref 
    target="RFC6724"/> Source Address Selection Rule 8 when 
    selecting a default source address among multiple choices and an application 
    has not explicitly indicate what kind of source address it prefers.
   </t>
    <t><list>
      <t>[Editor's note: Describe the 'prefix Class' usage when doing address
      selection and how applications can make use of it.]</t>
    </list></t>
   </section>



  </section>

  <section title="Security Considerations">
   <t>Existing Prefix Information Option related security considerations
   apply as described in <xref target="RFC4861"/> and <xref target="RFC4191"/>.
   A malicious node on the shared link could include such 'mobility property' flags in a Prefix Information Option causing the host to learn wrong information regarding the prefix and thus make misguided selection of prefixes on the link. Similarly a malicious middleman on the link could modify 'mobility property' flags in a Prefix Information Option causing misguided selection of prefixes. In order to avoid on-link attacks, SeND <xref target="RFC3971"/> can be used to reject Router Advertisements from potentially malicious nodes and guarantee integrity protection of the Router Advertisements.   
   </t>
  </section>
        
  <section title="IANA Considerations">
   <t><xref target="piomt"/> defines a new IPv6 Neighbor
   Discovery protocol option type TBD1 for the Prefix Information Option with
   Meta Data. The type value is defined in the existing 'IPv6 Neighbor Discovery
   Option Formats' IANA registry.
   </t>
   <t><xref target="suboptions"/> defines a new IANA registry for the Prefix 
   Information Option with Meta Data suboptions. The registry allocation policy
   is Standards Action <xref target="RFC5226"/>. The initial allocations are
   for the prefix properties and prefix class suboptions are listed in
   <xref target="suboptions"/>.
   </t>
  </section>
        
  <section title="Acknowledgements">
   <t>The authors thank Ole Troan for his feedback and suggestions on this
      document (the Classed PIO).
   </t>
  </section>
 </middle>

 <back>
  <references title="Normative References">
   &RFC2119;
   &RFC4861;
   &RFC4862;
   &RFC6724;
   &RFC5226;
  </references>
  <references title="Informative References">
   &RFC5014;
   &RFC3493;
   &RFC6275;
   &RFC4191;
   &RFC3971;
   &RFC5213;
   &RFC3549;
   &API;
   &CLASS;

   <reference anchor='TS.29274'> 
      <front> 
       <title>3GPP Evolved Packet System (EPS); 
		 	  Evolved General Packet Radio Service (GPRS) 
		 	 Tunnelling Protocol for Control plane (GTPv2-C)
       </title> 
      <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author> 
      <date day='22' month='December' year='2010' /> 
      </front> 
 
      <seriesInfo name='3GPP TS' value='29.060 8.11.0' /> 
      <format type='HTML' target='http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/29060.htm' /> 
   </reference> 

   <reference anchor='I-D.damic-6man-pmip6-ind'> 
    <front>
     <title>Proxy Mobile IPv6 indication and discovery</title>
     <author initials="D" surname="Damic" fullname="Damjam Damic">
      <organization/>
     </author>
     <date month="March" year="2009"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-damic-6man-pmip6-ind-00"/>
    <format type="TXT" target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-damic-6man-pmip6-ind-00"/>
   </reference>
  </references>
 </back>
</rfc>

